Everyone's always obsessed with where
you should enter your trades, but where
you exit your trades is just as
important. And for most traders, their
exits are absolutely shocking. And when
you ask them why they chose to exit
where they did, it just ends up sounding
like a bunch of excuses or justifying
themselves after the fact, rather than
having a clear logical reason why that
was the exact moment to exit a trade.
But the thing is, if you don't get your
trade exits right, then your performance
is going to be terrible. There's no two
ways about it. It doesn't matter how
great your opportunities are, if you're
closing them at the wrong time, you're
not going to have good results. So,
let's try and solve that in this video.
So, there are three main logical reasons
to exit a trade. Because there's
negative expectancy, because of a
forcing point, or because of the time
horizon. And to be clear, when I say
main reasons, there are other logical
reasons as well, but they'll usually
either directly or indirectly relate to
these three. So, these are the main
ones. And if all you ever did was just
focus on understanding these and stick
to these three reasons and nothing else,
your trade exits would be absolutely
fine and your performance would be much
better than most traders.
So, I'm going to explain these three to
you and the logic behind them. And to
get to that point, we're going to start
off by understanding what it is that
most traders are currently doing, what
you're likely to be doing at the moment,
why it's a mistake and why it's
illogical. And by walking you through
that step by step, you're going to
automatically understand why these are
logical and hopefully that will lead you
to sticking with them. So, when we talk
about logic in trading,
I always like to refer to this concept
here, implicit statements. If you've
watched my videos before, you would have
heard me talk about this. In fact, last
year I did a whole long video about it,
which you can find on the channel if you
haven't watched it already. There was
only seven videos released last year, so
it's easy to find. It's one of those
ones. But the basic idea is that every
time we make a decision and take an
action in the markets, whether we
realize it or not, we are making a
statement. And an action could be
entering a trade, exiting a trade,
scaling and scaling out, moving our stop
loss. So, we always need to make sure
that those statements are logical, so
they make sense, and they're
intentional. So the statement we're
making through our action is what we're
meaning to say, like the thing that
we're thinking is being expressed
through our actions. Because what you
find is that most traders aren't making
logical statements, they're not aware of
the statement they're making, what they
think they're stating through an action
is different to what they actually
think, and obviously your actions will
speak louder than words in the markets.
And when this is the case, it destroys
your performance. It means you're
unlikely to be consistent, therefore
your performance is going to be worse.
And the data that you collect from your
trading, which you then want to use to
improve what you're doing, to figure out
what's working, what needs to change,
where there are skill gaps, is going to
be just noise. So the conclusions that
you draw from it are not going to be
correct. Whereas if you follow a logical
framework, and you're making the right
sort of statements, and you're aware of
the statements you're making, your
performance is going to be more
consistent, it's going to be better, and
your data is going to be more meaningful
and useful. So the conclusions that you
draw from your data are actually going
to help you to find improvements. You
can get better and better.
Now if you're listening to all this and
thinking, "Huh, what does that mean,
implicit statements?" then just go and
watch the other video about it. I'm not
going to go into a lot of detail about
it here. The thing I want to point out
is that when we exit a trade, we are
making a statement, and so I want us to
keep this in mind, because what I want
you to get to is the point where you're
aware of the statement you're making,
and it's the right one.
So think about this.
How do you think most traders are
deciding to exit their trades? What's
the main reasons that people have for
exiting a trade where they do? And what
is it that you're doing with your
trading at the moment? When are you
deciding to exit your trades?
Usually it's going to fall into one of
two categories.
Either it's that you don't believe that
it's going to move further into profit,
so you're exiting before it reverses
against you, or the price has reached
your profit target, a target that you
set at the point of entering, maybe with
a take profit level that took you out
automatically.
So we're going to go through each of
these, and we're going to start with
this one here, that you don't believe it
will move further into profit. So just a
little example for you here. Let's say
that you're entering long down here and
you thought it had potential to reach
the top of the sort of range that we
were in, but it reached the point where
price is clearly struggling, momentum
dies off there, it starts reversing a
bit against you and you think, "Okay,
it's run its course. I'm going to exit
the trade here because I don't think
it's going to move any further into
profit."
So, what do you think the problem is
with this? Why is this an illogical
approach? Because on face value it
sounds fair enough. Like, of course, if
I don't think it's going to move any
further, I'm going to get out of the
trade.
Well, think about the cliché that you
hear everyone going on about these days,
that trading is a game of probabilities.
Everyone on YouTube and Instagram says
this. Obviously, people in the trading
space, not everyone, that would be
weird.
But, I've talked about this before and
you might have heard me say that when
people say that trading is a game of
probabilities, I say, "Yeah, I agree.
Not so much that it's a game, but it is
about probabilities." But, in that case,
where the [__] are probabilities in all
of the work that you're doing? Where are
probabilities in your analysis? In your
reason for entering a trade? In how you
review your trades? In how you find
improvements? Where are probabilities?
Cuz all I ever see is success rate,
which is not the same as probabilities.
I've explained why in previous videos. I
won't go into it for now. But, I never
see probabilities.
But, we all accept that trading is about
probabilities.
So, if this is the case, then we know
that we can't predict the future with
absolute 100% certainty, not in the
markets, and we shouldn't be trying to
either. I know a lot of people do.
Obviously, if you're choosing to exit a
trade there because you think the price
is not going to move any further, you're
making a prediction about what you think
is going to happen next. Likewise, a lot
of traders enter trades because they
think the price is going to move into
profit for them.
But, that's not possible in a situation
where it's based on probabilities, where
there's a chance of one outcome or
another. Like, think about if we were
flipping a coin and it's fairly
weighted, so 50% chance of heads, 50%
chance of tails, and I say, "No, this
definitely going to land on tails." And
then it does land on tails, and I go,
"See, I told you I was right. I just
knew it." What are you going to think
about that?
Well, you're not going to think that I
was right. I mean, technically I was,
but I wasn't right that it was
definitely going to land on tails. There
was a 50/50 chance, and on that
occasion, I was on the right side of
that. But, if I keep doing that over and
over again on every coin flip, I say
definitely tails, definitely heads, how
often do you think I'm going to be right
over the long run?
Around 50%, right? And it's the same in
the markets.
If you say this is what's going to
happen next, sometimes it will and
you'll think that you were right. And
the times it doesn't, you'll think you
were wrong. But, really on average, it's
going to end up at the probabilities. If
you were sitting there thinking you're
Nostradamus, like this fella here,
and trying to predict exactly what's
going to happen in the future with
certainty, well, as long as you have a
hole in your ass, you're not going to be
able to achieve it. You're going to be
wrong a lot, and it's not the right way
to be approaching the markets because we
can't predict with certainty.
So, if trading is about probabilities,
and we know we can't predict the future
with certainty,
that means that we accept that there is
a probability of a bullish move and a
probability of a bearish move.
So, if I ask you,
what's the chance of price moving up
from here compared to moving down,
then what's the first thing you're going
to ask me?
How far up or down? Cuz that really is
going to change things a lot, isn't it?
So, you can't just say, like, what's the
probability of a bullish move compared
to a bearish move cuz it depends on how
far we're looking at. So, if we're
looking at this example here, and we're
saying we don't believe it will move
further, whatever ever again, that's it
forever now? Or are we talking in terms
of outcomes? Are we saying the
the comparison between moving all the
way back to our entry point compared to
towards the top of the range? Like, what
are we looking at here? We have to
define our outcomes.
And so, if we're accepting that trading
is about probabilities, we can't predict
the future with certainty, we know
there's a chance for bullish move and a
bearish move, and the only way we can
figure out the chance of each is by
defining what those outcomes are,
then what we're left with is this
calculation here, trade expectancy
calculation. And this is the calculation
that you should be using for deciding
when to enter trades as well as when to
exit trades. And I'll give you a simple
example. Let's say that we're flipping a
coin,
okay, and we've again tested it. We know
for sure it's 50% chance of heads, 50%
chance of tails.
Now, you and I are going to play a coin
flipping game, but the rules are going
to change throughout the game, and you
can decide when you want to play and
when you don't want to play. So, we
start the game where if it lands on one
side,
I'm going to pay you £10, and if it
lands on the other side, you're going to
pay me £10. So, you're going to lose
£10.
And I say, "Do you want to play the
game?"
Well, you're going to say, "No." Because
if we think about the positive outcome
for you is going to be 10, the
probability is 50%, so 0.5.
Negative outcome is also going to be 10
multiplied by 0.5. What's the
expectancy? Zero. Okay? So, there's no
point you playing.
Now, after a couple of flips, we change
it and we say, "Okay, now
if you lose, you're going to pay me £10.
If you win,
I'm going to pay you £20. So, now your
positive outcome is 20 * 0.5, so that's
going to be 10
minus 10 multiplied by 0.5 is five. So,
you have positive expectancy here. So,
you're going to be playing."
And at what point do you think that you
will stop playing?
Well, you will stop playing either when
it returns to this, when there's no
point, or when it's flipped the other
way where I'm going to
give you £10 and you're going to give me
£20. Why? Because the calculation is the
other way around. So, here it'll be 10 *
0.5
20 * 0.5, and what you're going to end
up with
is a negative number. So, that means
every time the that we flip the coin,
every time you play the game, we don't
know on that individual game whether
you're going to lose money or gain
money, but the longer we go on, because
you have negative expectancy, over time
you're going to lose money, so there's
no point playing.
So, that means you choose to play when
you have positive expectancy, you choose
not to play when you have negative
expectancy, or this which we call the
base rate. I'm not going to explain
everything in this video because I've
explained these terms in other videos.
But essentially, this is what we should
be doing for our trading as well. We
know that at any time there are going to
be
positive outcomes and probabilities of
those, negative outcomes and
probabilities of those, and we should be
in trades when it's positive expectancy
and not in trades when it's not.
But the problem is
most traders are not able to do this.
They can't take this approach because
they're following predefined set of
criteria to enter trades, which they
call strategies, which are not
strategies at all, and we'll talk about
that in another video. And they have no
real understanding of the context. So,
what they're doing is looking at what's
similar in a situation, but let's say
I've got this list of
five different entry criteria, 1 2 3 4
5. Okay, so when these things happen,
it's telling me I need to enter a trade
long.
Well, I'm saying that these five
factors, the things that are similar in
each of the situations I'm looking at,
are the only things that impact
probabilities, and everything else
doesn't matter.
Whereas when you learn to look at the
full context, you don't just look at the
similarities, you also look at the
things that are different, and you get a
full view of the situation,
at which point you can then plan where
the meaningful potential outcomes are,
and estimate what the probabilities of
those are. Then you can run that through
the calculation and decide, "Okay, it's
positive expectancy, I'll enter the
trade." Or "It's not positive
expectancy, I won't enter the trade."
And likewise, as price moving and it
reaches a certain point, and you run
through the calculations again, you
might realize that now it's negative
expectancy, and you get out of the
trade.
But most traders can't do this cuz they
are not analyzing the markets
completely. They're They're just
spotting, plotting, and labeling things
on the charts, playing an adult's
version of Where's Wally, and entering
basically when a pattern matches what
they're looking for. And I don't
necessarily mean chart pattern, but like
a pattern of price behavior. Okay, this
zone and this candle formation, enter a
trade.
Now, if you want to learn how to do
things the right way, cuz I'm not going
to explain everything in this video,
then check out the free training series
that's linked in the description box.
It's pretty comprehensive, and I just
put it together this year, so I'd
definitely recommend signing up. It's
free, you might as well.
Okay, so already, hopefully, you can
start to see the logic that if we
understand that that there's a
probability of different price moves,
that there are no absolutes, then we
need to be thinking about things in
terms of this calculation. But, we can
go a level deeper, cuz it's not just
about this. There's more going on than
just that. So, here's the thing.
Our brains process situations
differently, depending on whether it's
an ambiguous uncertainty, and we could
just call that an uncertainty, or a
risk. Now, this was first sort of
defined many, many decades ago by a guy
called Frank Knight, and he said that a
risk is when the probabilities of future
events can be estimated, and an
uncertainty is when we have no grasp of
the probabilities or the outcomes. In
some cases, you don't even know the
outcomes, and of course, it's an
uncertainty.
So, that was many decades ago that he
defined it in that way, but since then,
it's actually been studied extensively.
And from a sort of neurological point of
view,
it's been found that when a situation is
an uncertainty,
then our brain is going to process it
differently to when it's a risk. And
when it's an uncertainty, in terms of
the areas of our brain that are more
active and the processes that take
place, we have more emotional and threat
detection processing taking place.
Whereas, when it's a risk, we have more
rational processing taking place. So,
the difference between the two of them
is about probabilities. And so, in terms
of our trading, if we want to have more
rational processing, rather than
emotional processing, then we need to be
estimating the probabilities. I'll give
you like a really simple
example to to help you understand the
difference between the two. So, imagine
that you open a door, walk into a room
and it's pitch black. You can't see a
thing and you can just hear this
aggressive growling somewhere in the
room with you. Imagine what you're going
to be feeling in that moment. It's pitch
black, you can't see where the thing is,
if it's close to you, what it is. You
just hear that growling. You're going to
be anxious, you're going to be scared,
you're going to be trying to get out of
the room, right?
Whereas, if you open a door, the lights
are on and you see there's this little
dog in the corner chained up and he's
growling because he's been abandoned and
he's scared. He can't attack you, he's
not close to you. You can see that from
how long the chain is. But, what are you
going to be feeling in that moment? You
can think about it more rationally, more
logically. You could probably feel sorry
for the dog rather than being afraid and
trying to get out of the room. You
probably want to see how you can help
it.
So, that's the difference. I know it's a
bit of a weird one. That's the
difference between an uncertainty and a
risk. You can make more rational
decisions or you'll end up making
irrational decisions, basically
emotionally charged decisions, which is
what we'll come on to.
But, just to point out, there is
something else that happens and it's
something that leads traders hesitating
when opening trades. And we have a whole
video about this on the channel about
why you hesitate when opening trades.
But, basically when you're thinking in
terms of absolutes, what you're looking
for is certainty in a situation where
you're not going to find it. And in an
uncertain situation, the way that our
brains have developed to deal with it is
to go through a process known as explore
exploit. So, you can think of it like
our ancestors, if they were out there
not living in houses, but living on the
land and trying to find a safe place to
dwell, then they'd be on the search for
somewhere where they can have shelter,
where there aren't going to be major
predators around, where they have a
water source, where they have food. And
once they find that, when they've
explored and found that thing, they'll
exploit. They won't go, "Oh, that's
quite nice, but let's keep going in case
we find something better." No, they
exploit first and then once they're
comfortable, maybe then they go go
explore for something better.
But, in a situation where it's going to
be endless uncertainty, you'll stay
locked in the explore phase
indefinitely. And what you'll be doing
is looking for more and more
information, scouring different signs
and cues to try and find the certainty
that you're looking for, which you will
never find. And this is why traders then
hesitate to open trades and will, you
know, go online see what other people
are thinking, add more levels onto their
chart, more indicators, just trying to
layer on things, hoping that at some
point they'll feel that sense of
certainty. When actually all they end up
doing is either confusing themselves or
just getting a false sense of
confidence.
But, this is something we won't discuss
for now, but just to be aware of it. Uh
this is more about the trade entry, but
it does also happen with a trade exit.
But, with the trade exit something
a bit different to that takes place.
Because, you know, we said here that if
you are not transforming something into
a risk by estimating the probabilities,
you're going to have a more emotionally
charged decision. But, there's more to
it than that when you have a trade open.
Because, the thing is
the same neural circuits that trigger
when we're physically threatened
are also triggered when we're threatened
in other ways, such as emotionally,
socially, but also financially. So, we
have like a very ancient brain. And the
way that our brains process financial
danger is the same way as if we're, you
know, in physical danger that someone's
going to hit us or attack us or
something like that. Okay? So, we go
into fight or flight mode, things like
that. So, if you think about when you
have a trade open and things suddenly
change to being quite risky, like it's
more volatile, you've got more at risk
or something like that. What ends up
happening?
Palms go sweaty, feet get clammy, a bit
cold, might need to go to the toilet
more often. Talked about all of this on
the channel as well in the past. But,
that's because your brain is processing
it in the same way as a physical danger.
And so,
if you think about things in terms of
physical danger,
when are those feelings going to be more
heightened?
Well, it's going to be based on the more
danger there is. And so,
it's the same for financial risk. That
all of these reactions are going to be
heightened more based on the level of
risk that we have. Okay? So,
in these situations when we're in
danger, we revert to survival instincts.
And our prefrontal cortex, that's going
to be processing in a more rational way,
effectively starts to go offline and we
start to have these survival instincts
which just save us from the situation.
So, if you imagine you have a trade
where
something's really risky, what's the
easiest way to survive that situation?
Get out of it, right? Now, the thing
about trading is that in many ways, if
you want to trade properly in a logical
way to make decisions that make sense,
you have to do things that are
counterintuitive for our survival
instincts. You have to think about
things in a different way. And when you
follow the right logical model, a lot of
these sort of instincts that disrupt
your trading go away because you are
changing things into probabilities, into
logic, and you can think through things
more rationally than if you're not, if
you're just trying to decide what you
think is going to happen next. So, if we
accept that our brain is going to be
more emotional, more survival-oriented
when we have a higher level of risk,
well, let's think about what happens
when we have a trade open.
So, when we're talking about choosing
the point to exit trades, we're talking
normally about it moving into profit
because often if it's moving into a
loss, you'll have your stop loss there
that will take you out of the trade or
at least like a predefined exit point
where you say, "Okay, beyond that point,
there's no point being in this trade."
But what happens with your profitable
trade?
Let's think about this.
As the trade moves further and further
into profit, you're going from having
low profit
all the way up to high profit, okay? And
we're going to call this
running profit. Excuse my terrible
handwriting all the time.
Now, what's happening at the same time
as that?
As our profit is increasing,
something is going from being high
all the way down to being low.
And that thing
is our impulse control.
Why?
Because as the profit that we have
running is increasing, we have more that
we can lose. And therefore our feelings
of loss aversion and things like that
are going to be kicking in more and
more, and we want to protect the profit
we have rather than losing it. So, it's
not about having an actual loss on the
account, but it's losing something that
we currently have. So, the higher this
gets, the more our impulse control is
lowering because the more we start to go
into those five ways things, the more
we're having emotionally charged
decisions.
And so, this is going to increase this
even more.
Okay? So, in those situations where
you're not turning something into a
probability,
you're already going to have more
emotional threat detection type
processing, less rational processing.
So, that's already leading to
emotionally charged decision.
Then, because our brains process
financial danger in the same way to
physical danger, as that financial
danger increases, the risk level
increases,
which what happens when we have a
running profit, is adding to this even
more.
So, then we come to the key question,
which is
when we are making this decision to exit
a trade because we don't really believe
it will move further into profit,
is the right statement being made?
Well, first of all, if we're not
thinking in terms of probabilities, the
chances are quite slim that we're making
the right statement in that case.
But also, when you take into account the
emotionally charged decision, because
I'm struggling to say that phrase,
because of all of these factors sort of
compounding it and making it more and
more emotionally charged,
then what do you think we might be doing
in that situation?
Do you think we're exiting because we
don't think it's going to be moving
further into profit, or do you think
we're picking up on certain factors in
that market, and our survival instinct
is kicking in, and rather than enduring
danger, we're wanting to escape it and
we're exiting?
Now, a funny thing happens with our
brains.
Our brains There's a part of our brain
is basically like a narrative creating
machine. And we create narratives about
what we're doing in our life in the
world around us to make us feel more
stable and comfortable. And there have
been studies on traders, and I won't
explain the whole study, but basically
it's found that people will make
decisions based on stress levels or
volatility in the markets, things that's
like an instinct type approach. And then
afterwards, when they're asked to
explain why they did what they did, they
will create a narrative that tries to to
explain it, that gives some logic to it.
When really they can tell from the data
that actually that wasn't the reason
that they were making that decision, it
was something else. And so this is
exactly what happens with your trading
or with most people's trading, that if
you are not changing things into
probabilities and making decisions to
exit a trade when it's negative
expectancy or when it's just not
positive expectancy, but instead you're
making this determination about price is
not going to move further into profit
because of all these emotions, you're
more likely exiting at the wrong time
and then justifying after the fact. And
that's why people's explanations about
their trade exits often just sound like
excuses because deep down people don't
really know why they're exiting trades
what at that time. They don't sort of
predefine it. They don't have these
rules that really clearly specify it in
a logical way. They're just thinking,
"Oh, it's not going to go any further.
Get out of the trade."
So, chance of making the right statement
very low. Chance of hesitating all the
time, confusing yourself, having poor
performance,
uh ending up when the price moves
further into profit saying, "Oh, I made
a mistake. I should have stayed in
longer." And when it reverses saying,
"See, I told you so."
Very high.
Okay, so that's the first one. And
already now you should be able to see
why
one of the logical reasons to exit a
trade is about negative expectancy.
So, let's move on to the second one. The
second one is that price reaches your
profit target. So, in this case, you
entered the short trade here, and at the
time of entering in trade, you've
decided this is my stop loss,
and this is my profit target. And then
you can set a take profit level there,
so when the price reaches it, you're
taken out of trade automatically in a
profit. People love this approach, this
set and forget approach. People say,
"Oh, this is the ideal way to trade
because then you're not having to, you
know, make decisions when you're feeling
emotional, and blah, blah, blah." Now,
that's true. You're not going to be
making emotionally charged decisions at
this point, but it's still not logical.
Because if we know that
it's all about probabilities,
and that if something is positive
expectancy, we would want to be in a
trade, and if it's not positive
expectancy, we would want to be out of
the trade,
is this likely to be the exact moment
that is negative expectancy?
What do you think?
Now, it might be that at the time of
entering the trade, you figured that out
and you've said, "Okay, that will be
negative expectancy at that point, and
that's why I'm getting out of the trade
there."
Fair enough, right? And you might think,
"Well, that that now answers that, so as
long as you're taking that approach,
it's fine."
But that's not the case because there's
also something else that's illogical
about it.
Because if that's the case, you're
making a decision based on the wrong
context, and therefore you're like this
weird dude here. You're You're trading
blindfolded because you're making
decisions without actually knowing what
you're making a decision about. So, in
this case, let's say that you've entered
a long trade here, and you've set a take
profit level here at the top of the
range, and the reason you've done this
because you're being a bit more advanced
and thinking through things in the right
sort of way, the reason that you've
chosen this because you think beyond
this point is going to be negative
expectancy. Okay, sounds good so far.
But what are you making that assessment
based on?
You're making that assessment based on
the context at this point here. So,
everything that's happened up until this
point, these are all the variables,
these are the contextual factors that
are leading you to making that
assessment. So, you are basically
assessing the probabilities, and of
course, to get to the probabilities, the
potential outcomes.
Based on price being down here and all
of this,
what do you not have when you're making
that decision?
Well, you don't have any of the context
between this point and this point.
What about if price reaches it by taking
forever
and getting up there like that compared
to a direct move like this, huge
momentum kicking in?
Do you really think that both of these
situations have the same probability of
the next potential outcomes?
Of course not. Not unless you're [__]
mental, then fair enough. Then
you believe what you want to believe.
But of course not. Like we don't know
how price is going to approach this area
at this point in time down here. So, how
can we have any estimate about the
probabilities? Now, what you might have
at this point in time when you're
entering the trade is just an initial
estimate based on certain assumptions
that you can make where you say, "Okay,
if it's going to be the same sort of
activities we've had so far, if it
reached this point here, then the
advantage over base rate is going to be
to the downside, so it would be negative
expectancy for a move higher." Fine.
But the thing about estimating
probabilities is that as you get more
information, you have to update your
assessments. The way we assess
probabilities is based on something
called Bayes' rule where we're basically
taking a prior, which in our case would
be the base rate, so the probabilities
if there's no advantage,
we're then
assessing
all of the variables
that will impact the probabilities and
ending up with what we call the
posterior.
Now, what happens is that this then
becomes the prior
and we have new information that updates
it to create a new posterior. So, as
price is reaching this point, we have
new information we didn't have before,
therefore we can update our
probabilities and decide what action we
want to take up here. So, with all of
this in mind, if you're taking that sort
of set and forget approach, where you
set a profit target and you exit
regardless of what happens,
do you think there's a chance that
you're making the right statement?
There is a chance. It's slim to none.
But, if the right statement is exiting
at the earliest point where it's no
longer positive expectancy,
are you really going to be getting that
right planning it ahead of time?
No. 99% of the time you're going to be
wrong. You're either going to be exiting
too late where it's already changed to
negative expectancy a long time ago, and
therefore by holding those positions
over the long run, you'd actually be
losing money, okay?
Or you're exiting too soon where it's
still positive expectancy, and you're
basically capping the opportunity of
ever having these runaway trades that
end up with huge, huge profits. Where
you start off where you planned this
short-term opportunity that was positive
expectancy, price goes with momentum,
and you end up being at the starting
point of a brand new trend, where it
goes hundreds of pips, if not a thousand
pips, or something. You'll never have
those opportunities with a set and
forget approach. You'll never have an
accurate assessment of the expectancy at
the point of exiting the trade, because
you're planning it based on the wrong
context, and you're trading blind like
this guy here. By the way, you know
these stock images? Have you ever
wondered what it's like to be this old
guy like this? He is way too old to have
to turn up to a place in a suit that
doesn't fit in properly, and wear a
blindfold, and go around like this like
he's trying to find his way around.
Years ago, I went to a photo shoot for a
stock images, and they made me do some
cringey things. I had to be like waiter,
putting things down on the table.
There's one where I had to wear a
backpack and look over my shoulder, and
it was on a green screen, so they put me
in like some forest in the actual end
image. I look like I was in the Hobbit
or something, like I was going on an
adventure.
And when I was working in the bank,
people found that photo, and for a while
my nickname was backpack wanker.
So, I feel sorry for this little dude
here.
But, anyway.
So, now you can hopefully see why both
of these common approaches are
illogical.
And hopefully, you can also see why
making your decision based on negative
expectancy is logical. It makes sense
when we understand that the markets are
about probabilities. It makes sense when
we understand what it means from a
psychology point of view. It makes sense
when we understand the context at the
point of entering compared to the
context at the point of exiting. So
really, when you think about it, the
only logical reason to exit a trade
would typically be because there's now a
negative expectancy.
But, there are situations where you
might have positive expectancy and you
choose to exit anyway, and it can still
be logical.
And that would be for these two reasons
here.
Forcing points or the time horizon.
So, what's a forcing point?
A forcing point is a time where you have
to make a decision.
So, for example, this might be
end of session,
end of week.
It might be because economic data is
coming out.
It might be because there's some other
news coming out. It might be because you
need to leave the screen.
So, all of these, and there are more of
them, are points in time where you will
need to make a decision depending on
your trading approach. So, everyone will
trade in slightly different ways. For
some people, they have to go to work and
they won't be able to check the charts,
so they don't want to hold trades during
that time. Some people don't want to
hold trades overnight because they don't
want it to disrupt their sleep or they
don't want to, you know, miss something
that disrupts the trade during that time
they're not at the charts. Some people
don't want to hold trades over the
weekend because they'd rather relax over
the weekend or they're worried about the
gap up or gap down at the start of the
next week, and so on and so on. So,
depending on your trading approach,
there can be logical points where you
would exit a trade even if there's
positive expectancy.
And that's something that we're going to
talk about in a separate video or it's
in that free training that I mentioned
that you can find in the description
box.
And we're going to talk about something
that is called the strategy kernel.
Most traders, what they call a strategy
isn't a strategy at all.
At the heart of any good strategy,
there's a strategy kernel which is made
up of three elements that relate to each
other in this way.
So, we have what we call diagnosis.
This basically your analysis but looking
at the full context to truly understand
what's happening, not just looking for
what's similar that matches your entry
criteria, but the full situation.
This runs through we call your guiding
policy. I'm not going to write it
properly but guiding policy or guiding
principles. And then once you filter it
through that, it leads to coherent
actions.
So, this end thing is how you actually
execute your trade. This is your
analysis and the thing in between is
your trading approach that you filter
this through. So, not every situation is
going to be ideal for you. Not every
decision point is going to be the same
for each trader. It will depend on your
guiding policy as well as the diagnosis.
And that's what all of these things
relate to is that the better you
understand this, the better able you are
to make these decisions without it being
an emotionally charged decision. But
we'll talk about the strategy kernel in
a separate video and I'll make all of
this a lot clearer.
Let's move on to time horizon. There are
two aspects to this.
One is that the context has changed
and it doesn't match
your time horizon for your trading
approach. So, some people want to be in
and out of trades over the space of
hours. Some people want to hold on to
trades for days or weeks. They don't
like making quick decisions. Like a
whole bunch of things.
So, it could still be positive
expectancy but the context has changed
in a way that you realize that the next
outcomes are going to take a lot longer.
This trade's going to be I have a a
longer holding period than you first
thought. Okay? So, context change, which
leads into a longer holding period.
And there are two things here. So, one
is that it doesn't match your trading
approach.
And two is about opportunity cost.
So, the reality is when you have a trade
open, there's an opportunity cost there
in terms of your time, your attention,
your cognitive energy, and your capital.
And as much as lots of traders like to
open lots of different trades at the
same time, really they're spreading
themselves thin and they're not going to
be doing their best work. And if you
want to be fully analyzing the context
and estimating probabilities that you
can make real logical decisions and have
consistent performance, if you have
several trades open at the same time,
it's really going to diminish your
quality of of that work and it's going
to lead to you making bad decisions.
So, if you want to make the best
decisions, you should be focusing on one
market at a time. And if that's the
case, then there's an opportunity cost
for having that trade open because while
you have that trade, you're not focused
on other opportunities. So, when you
have a trade open, then not only are you
making a statement that is still
positive expectancy, you're also making
a statement that this is the best place
for my money, for my attention, for my
time. Because if there was a better
opportunity somewhere else, you should
be trading that one instead, right?
So, if you look at a trade and you
realize the holding period is going to
be too long and the return I'll make
during that period of time is too small
that the opportunity cost doesn't make
sense, then even though it's positive
expectancy, you can choose to exit that
trade and it'll be a logical decision
because you're thinking about the
alternatives that there are. Now, as
I've already mentioned in a separate
video, I'm going to explain the right
way to approach trading strategies and
how most traders get it wrong. And I'll
explain this strategy kernel to you. So,
then you'll be clearer about how your
trading approach is going to dictate
whether certain forcing points are
logical reasons to exit a trade for you
with how you're trading, and it will
help you to understand where certain
context changes mean that it's no longer
appropriate for your trading approach,
and that can be a logical reason to exit
because of the time horizon either being
much longer or much shorter.
And then in another video, we're going
to go into a more a lot more detail
about the idea of opportunity cost and
what we call holding period return and
how to figure it out for your trading.
I'm going to tell you a funny little
story about a time that I made friends
with a bunch of strippers and they
taught me about strippernomics because
it's very relevant and who doesn't want
to have conversations like that. But
really as an overview, hopefully you've
gathered that the main point of this
session is that these are mistakes and
hopefully you can see why.
That the core thing you need to focus on
is exiting at the point that has
negative expectancy, which therefore is
going to dictate what sort of analysis
you have to continue doing when you're
in a trade, what sort sort of analysis
you should be doing when you're deciding
to enter a trade, what factors you need
to consider. If you want to understand
more about this, check out the free
training series that's in the
description box.
And in some situations when there's a
forcing point that can be a logical
reason to exit, when there are these
moments where something is happening
that is leading you to need to make a
decision, or when the time horizon has
changed because the context change means
it doesn't match your approach, or the
holding period means that the
opportunity cost is now too high that
you think it's better that you focus
elsewhere. And really if you can stick
to these three, especially that first
one, you are going to be absolutely
fine. But listen, go and check out that
training series that's linked down
below. And what I'm going to do now is
put two videos on screen. One is going
to be about implicit statements like I
talked about earlier, if you haven't
seen that one yet. And the other one is
going to be all about using probability
estimates in the markets because I'm
sure that if you're hearing about this
for the first time, you're going to have
objections, doubts, questions, and that
video covers a lot of it. So,
thanks for watching. See you soon.